<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>w5 | Seminar in Cognitive Modelling</title>
    <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w5/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>w5</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/media/icon_hu9107f20a553ba23fec53c69f31ee61df_369781_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>w5</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w5/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Objects &amp; Events</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/objects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Light hits our eyes  and somehow we perceive 3 dimensional &amp;lsquo;objects&amp;rsquo;.
What is an object?
In representational systems like programming languages, objects are core structure.
Is the same true for our cognitive system? Are objects learned or innate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to object, events seem like a great candidate for an ontological type. Formal semanticists have illustrated time and time again that they are important for explaining language. But are events core conceptual knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Spelke, E.S. (1990)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Principles of object perception. &lt;em&gt;Cognitive Science&lt;/em&gt;, 14(1), 29-56.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Zacks, J. M., &amp;amp; Tversky, B. (2001)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Event structure in perception and conception. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, 127(1), 3.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This article discusses the importance of event structure in perception, comprehension, memory, planning, and action. It suggests that events, like objects, have categories and parts, and understanding these relationships can enhance cognitive processes. The article explores the hierarchical nature of events and how they can be categorized and segmented based on different factors. It also discusses the role of language in event perception and the influence of goals and causal interactions on event recognition. The text highlights the similarities and differences between objects and events and emphasizes the importance of structured representations in understanding and remembering events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article also discusses the role of event schemata and goals in comprehension and memory recall. It further explores how event perception and cognition involve the interaction of different information sources and the limitations of hierarchical partonomic hierarchies. The article concludes with a list of references related to event perception, cognition, and memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt; --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate at least two of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Fillmore, C. J. (1970)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The grammar of hitting and breaking. &lt;em&gt;Readings in English Transformational Grammar&lt;/em&gt;, 120-133. (on Learn)&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This research explores the distinction between implicit and explicit knowledge of language, focusing on the verbs &amp;ldquo;hit&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;break&amp;rdquo; in English. Fillmore argues that while speakers may struggle to explain the usage and meaning of these words, they rarely make mistakes when using them. He emphasizes the need for linguistic observations to be incorporated into an empirical theory of linguistic structure. It explores the ambiguity of sentences and the role of body-part nouns in indicating places rather than objects.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Lettvin, J. Y. et al., (1957)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;What the frog&amp;rsquo;s eye tells the frog&amp;rsquo;s brain. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IRE&lt;/em&gt;, 47(11), 1940-1951.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  This paper presents research on the activity of single fibers in the optic nerve of frogs. The authors investigate what kind of stimulus causes the largest activity in one nerve fiber and what aspect of that stimulus is most excitatory. They find that the pattern of local variation in intensity, rather than the light intensity itself, is the most excitatory factor for the frog&amp;rsquo;s eye. The study provides a detailed analysis of the anatomy, physiology, and behavior of the frog&amp;rsquo;s visual apparatus. The research emphasizes that the frog&amp;rsquo;s eye informs the brain about the visual image in terms of local pattern, independent of average illumination. The findings suggest that the frog&amp;rsquo;s visual system is highly organized and interpreted, and not simply transmitting an accurate copy of the distribution of light.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Biederman, I. (1987)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Recognition-by-Components: A Theory of Human Image Understanding. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt;, 94(2), 115.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This article discusses the theory of recognition-by-components (RBC) in human image understanding. The theory proposes that objects are perceived by segmenting the input image into simple geometric components called geons. These geons can be derived from the contrasts of certain properties of edges in the image. The theory suggests that object recognition is robust and invariant to changes in viewing position and image quality. Experimental findings support the theory.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Scholl, Brian J. (2007)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Object persistence in philosophy and psychology. &lt;em&gt;Mind &amp;amp; Language&lt;/em&gt;, 22(5), 563-591.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  This article explores the concept of object persistence in both philosophy and psychology. It suggests that there are similarities between these two fields, indicating that psychological mechanisms may underlie the intuitions about persistence that fuel metaphysical theories. The goal is to bridge the gap between cognitive science and metaphysics and potentially contribute to philosophical progress. The article discusses themes such as spatiotemporal continuity, persistence through property change, and cohesion, and how these themes have led to empirical discoveries in psychological research. It also explores various scenarios and challenges our intuitions about the identity and persistence of objects over time. The article highlights the importance of cohesion as a principle for object persistence and discusses the role of intuitions and psychological mechanisms in influencing our judgments and interpretations. It also considers the potential for psychology to contribute to philosophy in understanding the origins of metaphysical intuitions.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- | 
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Cavanaugh, P. (2011) | &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Visual cognition. &lt;em&gt;Vision Research&lt;/em&gt;, 51(13), 1538-1551.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This article discusses various aspects of visual cognition, including visual executive functions, attention, object recognition, motion perception, and the role of shadows in perception. The authors highlight the need for further research in these areas to better understand the mechanisms underlying visual cognition and its interaction with other cognitive processes.
&lt;/details&gt;  | --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we represent object information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s missing from these representations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Events: linguistic artifact or core knowledge?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inductive Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/induction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/induction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While Sherlock&amp;rsquo;s over there blogging &lt;em&gt;The Science of Deduction&lt;/em&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;d argue most of human reasoning is &lt;strong&gt;inductive&lt;/strong&gt;. We see lot&amp;rsquo;s of examples (e.g., 10 million white swans) and then try to explain them (swans are white). Checks out, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Goodman, N. (1955)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The Riddle of Induction. Chapter 3 of &lt;em&gt;Fact, fiction, and forecast&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 59&amp;ndash;83). Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. (On Learn)&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;This is a classic. Nelson Goodman  was an influential philosopher of science (not to be confused with the living Standford based scientist Noah Goodman below). His thought experiment about Grue, in particular has been a persistant challenge for theories of induction.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Wason, P. C. (1960).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;On the failure to eliminate hypotheses in a conceptual task. &lt;em&gt;Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, 12(3), 129-140.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;This is another classic. Peter Wason who we met in Representation topic has had at least two lasting impacts on cogntibve science: One with his card selection task analysis and another with this inductive reasoning task.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- 
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  The article explores how the mind develops through the use of statistics, structure, and abstraction. It emphasizes the importance of understanding how the mind processes information and how it can be applied to various fields such as artificial intelligence and cognitive science. It focuses on the challenges of learning from sparse, noisy, and ambiguous data and highlights the ability of children to learn new words and concepts from just a few examples. It explains how Bayesian principles in the human mind are applied to specific cognitive capacities and modules. The article discusses the importance of abstract knowledge in learning, how learners acquire this knowledge, and different forms of abstract knowledge representation used in Bayesian cognitive models. It also discusses the concept of hierarchical Bayesian models and their role in learning abstract knowledge. The article concludes by highlighting the potential of Bayesian approaches in understanding cognition and its origins. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Tenenbaum, J. B., Kemp, C., Griffiths, T. L., &amp;amp; Goodman, N. D. (2011).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;How to grow a mind: Statistics, structure, and abstraction. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, 331(6022), 1279-1285.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Here&amp;rsquo;s another relatively modern paper as a comparison. Again it is interesting to compare the writing styles. It would seem like hierarchical Bayesian inference can help make more sense of how our inductive reasoning works, but does it really solve the riddle of induction? Note this paper is also quite relevant to the Rationality topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  The article explores how the mind develops through the use of statistics, structure, and abstraction. It emphasizes the importance of understanding how the mind processes information and how it can be applied to various fields such as artificial intelligence and cognitive science. It focuses on the challenges of learning from sparse, noisy, and ambiguous data and highlights the ability of children to learn new words and concepts from just a few examples. It explains how Bayesian principles in the human mind are applied to specific cognitive capacities and modules. The article discusses the importance of abstract knowledge in learning, how learners acquire this knowledge, and different forms of abstract knowledge representation used in Bayesian cognitive models. It also discusses the concept of hierarchical Bayesian models and their role in learning abstract knowledge. The article concludes by highlighting the potential of Bayesian approaches in understanding cognition and its origins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Goyal, A., &amp;amp; Bengio, Y. (2022).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Inductive biases for deep learning of higher-level cognition. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Royal Society A&lt;/em&gt;, 478 (20210068).&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  This paper examines the hypothesis that human and animal intelligence can be explained by a few principles. It focuses on the inductive biases used in deep learning for higher-level and sequential conscious processing in order to close the gap between current deep learning and human cognitive abilities. It emphasizes the need for additional inductive biases to achieve flexibility, robustness, and adaptability in deep learning models, particularly through knowledge representation. It also discusses the limitations of current machine learning systems in terms of their performance, generalizability, and robustness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Here&amp;rsquo;sa  recent paper by some of the big names in machine learning. It highlights very similar issues and solutions to problems of inductive generalization and the role of priors or inductive biases as arise in the human cognition literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How/do humans rationally solve the problem of induction?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are inductive biases and what are they good for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
