<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>w9 | Seminar in Cognitive Modelling</title>
    <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w9/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w9/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>w9</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/media/icon_huc79e2fc44413a67bc233ec068ab552e1_1379979_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>w9</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w9/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/space/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/space/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Space. The final frontier. How do we move in space? Vectors, scalars, navigation? Is spacial reasoning a cognitive instinct or a cognitive technology?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Pederson, E., Danziger, E., Wilkins, D., Levinson, S., Kita, S., &amp;amp; Senft, G. (1998)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Semantic typology and spatial conceptualization.  &lt;em&gt;Language&lt;/em&gt;, 74(3), 557-589.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Levinson, S., Meira, S., &amp;amp; The Language and Cognition Group. (2003)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Natural concepts&amp;rsquo; in the spatial topological domain-Adpositional meanings in crosslinguistic perspective. &lt;em&gt;Language&lt;/em&gt;, 485-516.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; In summary, the articles and content mentioned above explore various aspects of semantic typology, spatial adpositions, crosslinguistic comparisons, and the relationship between language, cognition, and spatial concepts. They discuss the challenges of categorizing and generalizing spatial adpositions, the role of methodology in comparative semantics research, the use of adpositions and locative nouns in different languages, and the exploration of adpositional groupings and semantic spaces. The articles also propose hypotheses, models, and statistical analyses to better understand the organization and universality of spatial concepts.
&lt;/details&gt;  --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Li, P., &amp;amp; Gleitman, L. (2002)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Turning the tables: Language and spatial reasoning. &lt;em&gt;Cognition&lt;/em&gt;, 83(3), 265-294.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This passage summarizes various research papers and studies that explore the effects of language on spatial organization, reasoning, and cognition. The Whorf-Sapir linguistic relativity hypothesis, which suggests that language influences thought, is discussed. The studies reviewed investigate how different languages use different spatial systems and how cultural factors can impact spatial terminology and cognitive strategies. The presence and suitability of local landmark cues are found to play a role in problem-solving strategies. The passage also mentions research on spatial reasoning in animals and prelinguistic infants, highlighting their ability to adapt spatial reasoning based on the presence of landmark cues. The authors emphasize the relationship between language and thought but note that human thought is robust to variation in linguistic usage patterns.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Levinson, S. C., Kita, S., Haun, D. B., &amp;amp; Rasch, B. H. (2002)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Returning the tables: Language affects spatial reasoning. &lt;em&gt;Cognition&lt;/em&gt;, 84(2), 155-188.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; The study explores the relationship between language and spatial reasoning, arguing against a cross-cultural comparison that suggests language has a causal effect on non-linguistic thinking. The authors conduct experiments to support their hypothesis that language does not have a direct effect on cognition in the spatial domain.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the natural concepts for space?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are spatial concepts a cognitive universal or driven by language?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/memory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Memory is the process of encoding, storing, and retrieving information when it is needed. This topic will explore the structure and function of memory in cognitive systems and relate it to the other themes of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Miller, G. A. (1956).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;The magical number seven, plus or minus two: Some limits on our capacity for processing information. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt;, 63(2), 81.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Collins, A. M., &amp;amp; Quillian, M. R. (1969).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Retrieval time from semantic memory. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior&lt;/em&gt;, 8(2), 240-247.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; The researchers, Collins and Quillian, conducted a series of experiments to investigate how people retrieve and process information from semantic memory. They proposed two hypotheses, the &amp;ldquo;unsuccessful search&amp;rdquo; hypothesis and the &amp;ldquo;search and destroy&amp;rdquo; hypothesis, to explain how individuals make judgments about the truth or falsity of sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiments yielded contradictory results to the researchers&amp;rsquo; initial hypothesis, leading them to develop the &amp;ldquo;search and destroy&amp;rdquo; hypothesis. This hypothesis suggests that individuals search for paths that connect the words in a sentence and reject the statement if they are unable to find a path that agrees with it.The researchers also discuss the issue of contradictions and emphasized that determining the falsity of a statement is not a simple process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt; --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate at least two of these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Atkinson, R. C., &amp;amp; Shiffrin, R. M. (1971).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;The control of short-term memory. &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt;, 225(2), 82-91.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This article explores the mechanisms and processes involved in short-term memory. The authors discuss the capacity, duration, and attentional control of short-term memory. They propose a model known as the modal model of memory, which explains how information is encoded and retrieved in short-term memory. This study provides valuable insights into the functioning of short-term memory and underlying cognitive processes. The research by Murdock, Tulving, and Glanzer focuses on the probability of recalling items in a list based on their position. They identify a primacy effect for the first few words and a recency effect for the last few words on the list, which is attributed to retrieval from short-term storage. They also propose a mathematical model to explain these effects, supported by experiments involving overt rehearsal during list presentation.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Collins, A. M., &amp;amp; Loftus, E. F. (1975).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;A spreading-activation theory of semantic processing. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt;, 82(6), 407.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This paper presents a spreading-activation theory of human semantic processing that can account for recent experimental findings. The theory extends Quillian&amp;rsquo;s theory of semantic memory search and priming, addressing misconceptions and proposing additional assumptions. It is shown to explain production and categorization experiments and critiques the Smith et al. model for categorization judgments. The theory suggests that activation spreads through a network of links in semantic memory, with activation decreasing as it moves outward. Concepts are stored in a lexical network based on similarity, and activation depends on priming and connections between concepts. The theory also discusses strategies for evaluating semantic matching and the role of properties and superordinate connections. It is applied to various experiments, including those on reaction times, category-instance relationships, negative instances, typicality, and semantic relatedness. The theory emphasizes the importance of considering different configurations of knowledge in memory and aims to provide a more powerful and flexible approach to understanding human semantic processing.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Zhang, W., &amp;amp; Luck, S. J. (2008).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Discrete fixed-resolution representations in visual working memory. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, 453(7192), 233-235.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Researchers have been debating whether working memory stores a fixed set of representations or a flexible pool of resources. This study aimed to resolve this controversy by conducting four experiments using a short-term recall paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of Experiment 1 showed that humans store high-resolution representations of some objects and no information about others, ruling out models with varying resolutions. Experiment 2 supported the idea of fixed-resolution representations, as precision did not decrease with set size. Experiment 3 found that resources were allocated to cued items, enhancing precision. Experiment 4 demonstrated that durable memory representations involve an all-or-none encoding process for simple objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the study supports the notion of a small number of fixed-resolution representations in working memory. These representations are not affected by set size and are created through an all-or-none encoding process. The experiments provide insights into the capacity and resolution of visual working memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the differences between short term and long term memory. How are they thought to be interrelated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does memory relate to the concepts, categories, learning and representation topics?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
