<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>w4 | Seminar in Cognitive Modelling</title>
    <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w4/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>w4</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/media/icon_huc79e2fc44413a67bc233ec068ab552e1_1379979_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>w4</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w4/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causality</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/causality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/causality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The search for a causal understanding of the world is at the heart of human cognition. It shapes learning throughout development and guides intelligent behaviour by allowing cognisers to predict outcomes, selectively gather information, attribute blame and credit, and imagine hypothetical and counterfactual situations. Causal reasoning is also central to the scientific method, underpinning how we, as scientists, design experiments, build and evaluate theories including the ones we use to describe and understand our own minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this session, we will think about how to model the cognition involved in learning, representing and exploiting a causal model of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Coenen, A., Rehder, B., &amp;amp; Gureckis, T. M. (2015).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Strategies to intervene on causal systems are adaptively selected. &lt;em&gt;Cognitive Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, 79, 102-133.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Pearl, J. (2019).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;The seven tools of causal inference, with reflections on machine learning. &lt;em&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/em&gt;, 62(3), 54-60.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This article explores obstacles in machine learning systems, such as adaptability, explainability, and cause-effect understanding, and proposes the use of causal modeling tools to overcome these challenges. It discusses the three-level hierarchy of causal reasoning, which involves association, intervention, and counterfactual thinking. Causal diagrams and structural causal models are presented as crucial tools for representing and estimating causal effects from data.
&lt;/details&gt;  --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate at least one of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Bramley, N. R., Lagnado, D. A., &amp;amp; Speekenbrink, M. (2015).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Conservative forgetful scholars: How people learn causal structure through sequences of interventions. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory and Cognition&lt;/em&gt;, 41(3), 708.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This article explores how people learn causal structures through interventions. The researchers developed a computer task where participants learned the structure of probabilistic causal systems. They developed models to understand participants&amp;rsquo; intervention choices and judgments, considering memory and processing limitations. The study found that successful participants used a model that maximized information gain, forgot evidence from earlier trials, and had conservative beliefs. The study highlights the importance of active learning and the use of simple heuristics in causal structure identification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Like Coenen et al, this is an example of human causal learning through interventions, at rung 2 of Pearl&amp;rsquo;s ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  Quillien, T., &amp;amp; Lucas, C. G. (2023).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Counterfactuals and the logic of causal selection. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Quillien and Lucas explore the relationship between counterfactuals and causal selection. They propose a counterfactual theory, suggesting that people imagine alternative possibilities and judge causal responsibility based on the correlation between factors across these simulations. The theory is supported by empirical data and experiments. The article discusses the use of a computational model, the Counterfactual Effect Size Model (CESM), to explain human judgments in various studies related to causal attributions and judgments. The CESM is found to have a good fit with the data and is able to predict participants&amp;rsquo; intuitions accurately.
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;  Pearl, J. (2000/2009)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Causality: Chapters 1-2. (On Learn)&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This important book laid formal/mathmatical groundwork for causal modelling in data science but also use of bayesian networks as representations of structural knowledge about the world, particularly causal, combining this with principles of probabilistic inference and statistical dependence. It is technical but readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Chapter one of the book introduces the concepts of probabilities, graphs, and causal models. It highlights the importance of probabilities in studying causality, especially in disciplines such as economics, epidemiology, sociology, and psychology. Probability theory helps determine the strength of causal connections and make inferences from noisy observations. The chapter also discusses the use of probabilities in handling exceptions that cannot be processed by deterministic logic. The passage goes on to introduce various concepts within probability theory such as axioms, conditional probabilities, Bayesian inference, joint distribution functions, and graphical models. It explains the properties and terminology associated with probabilities, graphs, and causal models. The chapter also explores the application of probabilities and causal models to hypothesis testing, interventions, and counterfactual analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, these chapters provide a comprehensive introduction to probabilities, graphs, and causal models, highlighting their applications and implications in studying causality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the levels of Pearl’s Ladder of Causation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes an intervention valuable?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are counterfactuals and what role do they play in reasoning?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/physics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From pouring a cup of coffee to playing frogger through the streets, physical reasoning is ubiquitous in human behavior. Arguably these goals have been stable throughout the evolution of our species, so are we optimal physical reasoners?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; McCloskey, M. (1983)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Intuitive physics. &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt;, 248(4), 122-131.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Battaglia, P. W., Hamrick, J. B., &amp;amp; Tenenbaum, J. B. (2013)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Simulation as an engine of physical scene understanding. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, 110(45), 18327-18332.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This research article introduces a model called the Intuitive Physics Engine (IPE) that uses approximate and probabilistic simulations to understand how people perceive and understand physical scenes. The model is based on computer engines used in video games and graphics and fits data from psychophysical tasks, captures illusions and biases, and explains core aspects of human mental models and common-sense reasoning. The article argues that understanding physical scenes is crucial for human interaction with the world and is linked to higher cognitive processes. The IPE model is shown to be able to compute intuitive inferences about scenes and capture how predictions are affected by factors such as object properties and applied forces.
&lt;/details&gt;  --&gt;
&lt;!-- | 
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; McCloskey, M. (1983) | &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Naive theories of motion. In &lt;em&gt;Mental Models&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 307-332). Psychology Press.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;   | --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Ludwin-Peery, E., Bramley, N. R., Davis, E., &amp;amp; Gureckis, T. M. (2020)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Broken physics: A conjunction fallacy effect in intuitive physical reasoning. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;, 31 (12), 1602-1611.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; The article investigates the conjunction fallacy in our ability to reason about physical events. Three experiments were conducted, and the results consistently showed that participants rated conjunction of two physical events as more likely than at least one of the constituent events in the same scenes. This raises questions about current theories of mental simulation in physical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Relating to the primary readings, does this fit better with McCloskey&amp;rsquo;s view that physical reasoning is based on heuristic rules, or Battaglia et al&amp;rsquo;s view that it is based on detailed simulations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Gerstenberg, T., Goodman, N. D., Lagnado, D. A., &amp;amp; Tenenbaum, J. B. (2021).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;A counterfactual simulation model of causal judgments for physical events. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt;, 128(5), 936.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
This article discusses the Counterfactual Simulation Model (CSM) and its application in understanding causal judgments in physical events. The CSM aims to predict how people make causal judgments by comparing what actually happened with what could have happened. The model is tested in experiments and provides a better fit than heuristic models. It captures different aspects of causation and can be used to model the semantics of causal verbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Relating to the Causality topic, what rung of causal reasoning is this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do humans represent physical knowledge and use that knowledge to achieve their goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are we optimal physical reasoners?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
