<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>w4 | Seminar in Cognitive Modelling</title>
    <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w4/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>w4</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/media/icon_hu9107f20a553ba23fec53c69f31ee61df_369781_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>w4</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/tag/w4/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 09:58:49 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mkunda.github.io/scm24/projects/physics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From pouring a cup of coffee to playing frogger through the streets, physical reasoning is ubiquitous in human behavior. Arguably these goals have been stable throughout the evolution of our species, so are we optimal physical reasoners?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;primary-readings&#34;&gt;Primary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should read these and be prepared to discuss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; McCloskey, M. (1983)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Intuitive physics. &lt;em&gt;Scientific American&lt;/em&gt;, 248(4), 122-131.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Battaglia, P. W., Hamrick, J. B., &amp;amp; Tenenbaum, J. B. (2013)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;Simulation as an engine of physical scene understanding. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, 110(45), 18327-18332.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; This research article introduces a model called the Intuitive Physics Engine (IPE) that uses approximate and probabilistic simulations to understand how people perceive and understand physical scenes. The model is based on computer engines used in video games and graphics and fits data from psychophysical tasks, captures illusions and biases, and explains core aspects of human mental models and common-sense reasoning. The article argues that understanding physical scenes is crucial for human interaction with the world and is linked to higher cognitive processes. The IPE model is shown to be able to compute intuitive inferences about scenes and capture how predictions are affected by factors such as object properties and applied forces.
&lt;/details&gt;  --&gt;
&lt;!-- | 
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; McCloskey, M. (1983) | &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Naive theories of motion. In &lt;em&gt;Mental Models&lt;/em&gt; (pp. 307-332). Psychology Press.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;   | --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secondary-readings&#34;&gt;Secondary Readings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presenter should read and incorporate these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Ludwin-Peery, E., Bramley, N. R., Davis, E., &amp;amp; Gureckis, T. M. (2020)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Broken physics: A conjunction fallacy effect in intuitive physical reasoning. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;, 31 (12), 1602-1611.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; The article investigates the conjunction fallacy in our ability to reason about physical events. Three experiments were conducted, and the results consistently showed that participants rated conjunction of two physical events as more likely than at least one of the constituent events in the same scenes. This raises questions about current theories of mental simulation in physical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Relating to the primary readings, does this fit better with McCloskey&amp;rsquo;s view that physical reasoning is based on heuristic rules, or Battaglia et al&amp;rsquo;s view that it is based on detailed simulations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:center&#34;&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-scroll  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Gerstenberg, T., Goodman, N. D., Lagnado, D. A., &amp;amp; Tenenbaum, J. B. (2021).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&#34;text-align:left&#34;&gt;&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;A counterfactual simulation model of causal judgments for physical events. &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt;, 128(5), 936.&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-robot  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
This article discusses the Counterfactual Simulation Model (CSM) and its application in understanding causal judgments in physical events. The CSM aims to predict how people make causal judgments by comparing what actually happened with what could have happened. The model is tested in experiments and provides a better fit than heuristic models. It captures different aspects of causation and can be used to model the semantics of causal verbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-chalkboard-teacher  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Relating to the Causality topic, what rung of causal reasoning is this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-under-discussion&#34;&gt;Questions under discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do humans represent physical knowledge and use that knowledge to achieve their goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are we optimal physical reasoners?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
